Inventory of the Tess Johnston Papers, 1929-2014
Hoover Institution Archives
Tess Johnston papers
1929-2014
2015C32
Hoover Institution Archives
21 manuscript boxes, 10 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder, and 1 hard drive (17.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photographs relating to Western communities and architecture in Shanghai and elsewhere in China. Mainly collected research material for publications by Tess Johnston.
Johnston, Tess
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical note
Chronology
1949 Graduated from Harrisonburg High School in Charlottesville, Viriginia.
1953 Joined the foreign service as an office secretary and was promoted to secretary to the consulate general in Dusseldorf, Germany.
1958-1967 Received Bachelor's Degree and Master's Degree in German from the University of Virginia.
1962-1967 Taught at the University of Virginia and at the College of William and Mary in Virginia.
1967 Joined the Agency for International Development in Vietnam.
1975 Rejoined Foreign Service, assigned to Consulate General in Frankfurt, Germany.
1976 Transferred to Embassy in East Berlin, Germany.
1978 Transferred to New Delhi, India.
1981-1986 First tour of duty in Shanghai.
1986 Named Foreign Service Secretary of the Year for her work coordinating the visit of President Ronald Reagan to Shanghai.
1986-1989 Acted as secretary to the administrative counselor at the United States Embassy in Paris, France.
1989 Second tour of duty in Shanghai.
1993 Co-founded Old China Hand Press with Er Dongqiang (also known as Deke Ehr)
1993 Published A Last Look: Western Architecture in Old China with Dongqiang Er.
1994 Published Near to Heaven: Western Architecture in China's Old Summer Resorts with Dongqiang Er.
1996 Published Far From Home: Western Architecture in China's Northern Treaty Ports with Dongqiang Er.
1996 Retired from the American Foreign Service.
1996 Published God And Country: Western Religious Architecture in Old China with Dongqiang Er (also known as Deke Erh).
1997 Published Welcome to Shanghai: A Guide for New Expatriate Residents To Help Them Make The Most of Their Shanghai Experience and The Last Colonies: Western Architecture in China's Southern Treaty Ports with Dongqiang Er.
2000 Published Frenchtown Shanghai: Western Architecture in Shanghai's Old French Concession with Dongqiang Er.
Scope and Contents note
Contains correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Western communities and architecture in Shanghai and elsewhere in China, mainly collected research material for publications by Tess Johnston.
The Personal Materials contains primarily correspondence and articles regarding Tess Johnston’s writings and research materials, including inquiries regarding various topics, as well as press and promotional materials for Johnston’s various writings. The Shanghai History includes books, articles, newsletters, clippings, expatriate association membership directories, printed matter, and various publications from the Old China Hand Press. Of note are the various memoirs written by family members detailing their experiences living as expatriates in China. The Photographs includes photographs of architecture and buildings taken by Tess Johnston in various cities around China in preparation for her books regarding European architecture in China.
Architecture--China.; China--History.; Europeans--China.; Shanghai (China)--History.
- Personal Materials, 1930-2010
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence and biographical materials.
  - Correspondence, 1986-2010 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Case audit files, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Membership directories and name lists, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 3: 2-5)
  - Clippings, book reviews and articles, 1994-2000 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
  - Press and promotional materials, 2009-2010 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Press and promotional materials, 1995-2005 (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
  - Faxes and articles written by Tess Johnston, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "President Bill Clinton's Visit", 1998 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Articles written by and regarding Tess Johnston, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Shanghai Art Deco manuscript, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
- Shanghai History, 1929-2012
  Maps, books, newspapers, manuscripts, memoirs, bank records, and correspondence regarding expatriate history in Shanghai.
  - Photocopies of street maps, sections 1-118, undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Two bound volumes of the North-China Herald, 1929-1931 (Box 5)
  - Two bound volumes of the North-China Herald, 1932-1933 (Box 6)
  - Two bound volumes of the North-China Herald, 1933-1934 (Box 7)
  - Two bound volumes of the North-China Herald April-September 1934 (Box 8)
  - Photocopy of 1947 Shanghai Street Directory, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Cosmopolitan Club of Wuhan bylaws, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Reprints on China: An annotated Catalog of Western language Reprints on China, circa 1990s (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Map of the Western Hills: Including a detailed description of the spots of interest and of the roads leading to same, 1935 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Travelers' Guide: Kiaochow-Tsinan Railway, 1931 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - City Guides and Descriptions of Theater Historian, circa 1920s (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - The China Magazine, November - December 1946 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Three books in Chinese, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 10: 7-9)
  - Two books in Chinese, 1990 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Directory of the China-America Council of Commerce and Industry, 1946 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - The China Weekly Review, 1931 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - The China Critic, 1931 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - "Consular List", 1956 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - "Cultural Cautions for U.S. Personnel Going to Southeast Asia" by John F. Embree, 1950 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - "Psychological Aspects of Foreign Aid and Development Programs", 1949 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - "The Concept of Pao as a Basis for Social Relations in China" by Lien-Sheng Yang, undated (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - "The Administration of Foreign Affairs" by Arthur W. Macmahon, 1951 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - "Destination Shanghai: Refuge for Stateless Jews", 1996 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - Copy of "The Chinese Jews" by Oliver Baimbridge, undated (Box-folder 11: 11)
    Photocopy from the National Geographic Magazine Volume XVIII, Number 10
  - Needham Research Institute newsletter, 2012 (Box-folder 11: 12)
  - Shanghai maps, undated (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Betwixt and Between by Margaret Sun, circa 1990s-2000s (Box-folder 11: 13)
  - The Shanghai Links Executive Community correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - "Waiting for the Glue Pot" by Kenneth R Peacock, 2011 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Copy of dissertation by Eduard Kögel titled "Zwei Poelzigschüler in der Emigration: Rudolf Hamburger und Richard Paulick zwischen Shanghai und Ost-Berlin", 2007 (Box-folder 12: 4-7)
    Materials in German
  - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - "History of Wuhu Hospital" by Elsie Hayes Landstrom, 1995 (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Photocopy of East Asian History journal, 1990 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - Copies of photos labeled "Angulo Pictures (social society)", undated (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - The China Connection newsletter, issues 3-58, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 13: 1-4)
  - China Gunboatman newsletter, 1991-2001 (Box-folder 13: 5-6)
  - Articles, bibliographies, and lists regarding Shanghai history, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Photocopies of photo album of Mukden and Harbin Treaty Ports, undated (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Consular General staff list and address list, 1998 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - Sasa News newsletter, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - Information regarding missions in China, 2002 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Bank records, 1934-1941 (Box-folder 14: 3-11)
  - Bank records, 1934-1941 (Box-folder 15: 1-8)
  - Bank records, 1939 (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
  - Street sections with old names, undated (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Rui Jin Guest House pamphlet, circa 2000s (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - Reproductions of maps of Shanghai, circa 2000s (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - Various magazines, including Shanghai Pictorial, one copy of Eastern Air, and one copy of China Review., 1992-1997 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - Kuliang Materials from Joan Jackson, undated (Box-folder 16: 9)
  - Book manuscript with Malcolm Rasholt, undated (Box-folder 16: 11)
  - Book manuscript with photographs by Malcolm Rosholt, undated (Box-folder 17: 1-4)
  - Various expatriate association membership directories, 1994-2008 (Box-folder 20: 3-4)
  - Correspondence with Reginald C. L. Van and photocopy of China Doctor by Raymond S. Moore, 1998 (Box-folder 20: 5)
  - American Chamber of Commerce in Shanghai Membership Directory, 2014 (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - American Women's Club of Shanghai Directory, 1998-2001 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Far From Home: Western Architecture in China's Northern Treaty Ports manuscript by Tess Johnston and Deke Erh, undated (Box-folder 21: 1-2)
  - StuDeO Studienwerk Deutsches Leben in Ostasien e.V., 2000-2014 (Box-folder 21: 3)
    Materials in German.
  - Clipping from the Shanghai Star, 1994 (Box-folder 21: 4)
  - Sheet music, undated (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Shanghai Library's English-language holdings, undated (Box-folder 21: 6)
  - Newsletter in Russian from the Association of Former Residents of China, 2014 (Box-folder 21: 7)
  - Old China Hands Reunion, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 8)
  - Book agreement and travel itinerary, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 21: 9)
  - Various newsletters, 2002 (Box-folder 21: 10)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 21: 11)
  - Copy of China Daily newspaper, 9/13/1991 (Box-folder 21: 12)
  - Embassy Court apartments materials, undated (Box-folder 21: 13)
  - Various materials regarding Shanghai architecture, 2002 (Box-folder 21: 14)
  - Expo 2010 Shanghai China (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - American Women's Club of Shanghai Directories, 2001-2013 (Box-folder 22: 3-6)
  - Key Officers of Foreign Service Posts, 1996 (Box-folder 22: 7)
  - The Old China Hand Gazette, 1995-2004 (Box-folder 22: 8)
  - Expatriate organizations membership directories, 1988-2006 (Box-folder 22: 9)
  - Tips for Consular Personnel Living in Shanghai, undated (Box-folder 22: 10)
  - Asia and the Pacific, McBlain books catalog 138, Circa 1990s (Box-folder 22: 11)
  - Various printed matter, including, History of Relations Between China and United States, Chinese Women's Club of Shanghai Annual Benefit Ball, The American Chamber of Commerce Bulletin, and Chinese Cities: a Geographical Reader, 1928-1936 (Box 23)
  - One bound volume of Finance and Commerce, 1941 (Box 24)
  - Includes four maps of Shanghai, photocopy of book in Chinese, manuscript of book titled Frenchtown Shanghai: Western Architecture in Shanghai's Old French Concession, Shanghai Talk newspaper, City documents from Harbin with translations from Russian, Circa 1990s (Box 25)
    Materials in Russian, and Chinese
  - Chinese Weekly Review, 1948 (Box 26)
  - Black photo album, undated (Box 27)
  - Photographs from balck photo album, 1928-1934 (Box-folder 28: 1-42)
  - Two newspaper clippings from black photo album, undated (Box-folder 28: 43)
  - Correspondence, 1937-2001
    - Correspondence from Joan Munday, 1987-2001 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - Correspondence from Jacqueline "Jackie" Tanner, 1998 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Various emails, 1992-2001 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - Correspondence and clippings regarding Rosholt, 1937-1997 (Box-folder 16: 10)
    - Shanghai postcards, undated (Box-folder 22: 2)
- Memoirs, 1998-2011
  Published and unpublished memoirs of expatriates in China.
  - Materials regarding Daisy Kwok, Circa 1990s (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - Only Trees Need Roots? by J.H. Jessen, undated (Box-folder 17: 6-7)
  - Only Trees Need Roots? by J.H. Jessen, undated (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - "Rambling Rose: The Life of Wilfred John Hubert Twilley", undated (Box-folder 18: 2)
  - Charles Campbell memoir, 1998 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - "The Life and Times of Oliver Cary Lockhart", undated (Box-folder 18: 4-5)
  - China Doctor: the Life Story of Harry Willis Miller by Raymond S. Moore, 1998 (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - "The Celestial City", undated (Box-folder 18: 7)
  - "The China Letters", undated (Box-folder 18: 8)
  - "Betwixt and Between" by Margaret Sun, undated (Box-folder 19: 1-2)
  - "Selling Souls in Sin City: Shanghai Singing and Dancing Girls in Print, Film, and Politics, 1920-1949" by Andrew D. Field, undated (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - Interview with Joyce Mayne, 1999 (Box-folder 19: 4)
  - Growing Up In Shanghai by Wolfgang Troeger, undated (Box-folder 19: 5-6)
  - "Highlights of a Life" by Mary Malcolm-Kluge, undated (Box-folder 19: 7)
  - John R. Rawlinson correspondence, 2002 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - Photocopies from Margaret Sun's book, undated (Box-folder 19: 9)
  - Memoir regarding Cuba by Liliane Willens, 2003 (Box-folder 19: 10)
  - "Russian Prostitution in Shanghai, 1920-1949" by Marcia R. Ristaino and various articles, 1998 (Box-folder 19: 11)
  - One Hard Boiled Egg! The Stories of Walter Palmer by Mike Palmer, manuscript and correspondence with author, 2011 (Box-folder 20: 1-2)
- Photographs, Circa 1990s
  Photographs of buildings from albums labeled "Former Treaty Ports"
  - Anhui, Circa 1990s (Box-folder 29: 1-8)
  - Dalian, undated (Box-folder 29: 9-19)
  - Harbin, Circa 1990s (Box-folder 29: 20-31)
  - Harbin, undated (Box-folder 30: 1-3)
  - Ningbo, undated (Box-folder 30: 4-5)
  - Tianjin, Circa 1990s (Box-folder 30: 6-17)
  - Qingdao, Circa 1990s (Box-folder 30: 18-26)
  - Wuhan, undated (Box-folder 30: 27-30)
  - Wuhan, undated (Box-folder 31: 1-11)
  - Xiamen, undated (Box-folder 31: 12-27)
  - Contains one copy of The Leader newspaper dated 1929 August 2, one map titled "Nanking-Shanghai and Shanghai-Hongchow-Ningpo Railways", and two newspaper clippings from Black Photo Album, 1929-1932 (Map case)
- Digital Media, undated
  Includes a hard drive and CDs. Remainder of collection not yet described.